OK, we had some technical difficulties at the end
of the first week's tutorial, so this is just a
few minutes showing off what I had hoped to
demonstrate live there. Now, as a reminder, the
activity we were playing with was based on the
roulette example, a form of a random walk, as we
will see soon, and specifically looking at
ways to numerically integrate the probability
distribution predicted by the central limit
theorem for a large number of spins of this
roulette wheel, a large number of repetitions of
our experiment, which give the probability for a
certain outcome how much money we win or more
likely lose. And on a reasonable computer system
like this one that's running Linux and this sort
of activity can be demonstrated just by directly
running Python on the code that has been set up to
solve that numerical integration as well as the
exact computation. Of the probability is figured
out beforehand and a cruder, constant
approximation that approximates the probability
distribution as a constant within each of these
intervals that define how much we win or lose. So
given five spins of that wheel. We immediately
recovered the plot that was shown at the end of
the tutorial showing all three of those
computations of the probabilities, the exact
values, the numerical integration based on the
central limit theorem and the constant
approximation to that. They are all coming out
quite close together. Most likely to lose a bit of
money and the approximation coming from the
central limit theorem, which becomes exact as the
value of N goes to infinity. Five is far from
infinity. So we have some small deviations from
that. If we look at the exact probabilities
compared to those coming from the central limit
theorem. You see that there are sort of
differences in the third decimal place and in
particular, the sum of the probabilities from the
central limit theorem are almost eight percent off
from adding up to one hundred percent that we
expect for a true probability probability
distribution. I can say if we just look at this
example of. N equals five spins four, which we
could write down all the probabilities exactly
pretty easily and compute them just with Wolfram
Alpha, a bit of typing to put in the expression
for the probability distribution from the central
limit theorem, which is just plugging in the
single spin machine minus five, three sevens and
variance, which is a hundred twenty five
multiplied by the number of spins and showing up
in the skeleton form. Exponential of X squared
gives us. These same numbers point zero three
seven five five for that first probability of
losing all five spins and thereby losing all
twenty five pounds, that our bet and also for all
six of the probabilities we get to that total sum,
ninety nine point two six percent. And just by
adjusting the limits of immigration there, the
advantage to programming this in Python, rather
than going through Wolfram Alpha or some fancy
calculator, is that it becomes trivial to rerun
this with a larger number of spins. Or we see
something that looks a bit more like a Gaussian
peaked at losing a somewhat larger amount of money.
And repeat that for. Five hundred or indeed five
thousand spins with. No further work getting to
the point where fifty thousand spins, there is
essentially 100 percent probability that we lose a
significant amount of money, no chance at all of
any gain. So we will look at python code in
general in more detail at the computer labs. I
have uploaded the code for this will revive
activity to the. Module's page on the Canada site,
just where we were, just there it is there for you,
you can't really do much with it on canvas apart
from copying it and putting it into something like
Google's collaboratory. Where? Can run and play
with this yourself. One thing will have to do is
change the argument passing rather than reading in
some number of spins. We just set that by hand. We
produce. The results you've already seen, both the
plot and all of those six probabilities computed
in three different ways within a second or two.
And if we come out of the printing out all of
these probabilities in each of the three different
ways of comparing them. We can quickly check that.
If a larger number of spin's.
The. Distributions do add up to one to a very good
approximation already. One other thing that might
be fun to see here is that if we get up to that
very large number, even though it still takes only
zero point eight seconds to run. We start having
errors pop up. Which are related to the binomial
coefficient that showed up in the exact
probability that was computed in the tutorial,
that probability is the binomial coefficient and
choose W for W wins and spins multiplied by the
power of winning each of those W spins, which is
eighteen thirty seven, slightly less than half,
also multiplied by the power of losing the minus W
other spins. That two is nineteen out of thirty
seven, slightly more than one half. But this
binomial coefficients involves in the factorial W
factorial and minus W factorial, I believe it is
right there and. Once again, it's up to this range
of thousands and factorial a thousand factories,
it becomes such a large number that it actually
overflows the number of integers that Python is
set up to handle without doing something special.
And that is the source of that error there, which
is something you may want to keep an eye out for
as you work on that computer project, but we have
seen just a quick look through the code that
involves some. Special functions that binomial
coefficient and numerical integration from a new
package called Scientific Python that you have in
addition to the numerical python and the
matplotlib that are discussed in the demo, I
should leave all of the details about this python
or any other examples for the computer lab coming
up soon.