Hello, I am David Schaich, pronounced as in 'handshake',
despite how it is spelled.  I am a Lecturer in
theoretical physics and I'm looking forward to
looking into statistical physics with all of you.
One thing I'll mention that interests me
about this topic is the concept of emergent
phenomena.  At the broadest level: large scale
behaviour that emerges from the dynamics of a large
number of underlying degrees of freedom that we
analyze with the tools and techniques of
statistical physics. Some examples of this that we
will see in the module are things like the laws of
thermodynamics, the ideal gas law, Planck's law --- but
this is a much broader concept that includes
things like superconductivity arising from an
electron gas in low-temperature materials; protons
and neutrons as emergent phenomena coming from
innumerable underlying quarks and gluons; or even
wormholes emerging from a statistical system --- which
was in the news just a couple of months ago.